<document>
  <title>Adoptive Dad Dreamed A Dream That Brought Him A Son</title>
  <date>April 12, 2013 </date>
  <urllink>http://www.npr.org/2013/04/12/176923820/adoptive-dad-dreamed-a-dream-that-brought-him-a-son</urllink>
  <audlink>http://pd.npr.org/anon.npr-mp3/npr/me/2013/04/20130412_me_14.mp3?dl=1</audlink>
  <transcript>
DAVID GREENE, HOST: 

 
On Friday mornings, we hear from StoryCorps, capturing conversations between loved ones across the country. Today's interview comes from Rochester, New York. That's were John Curtis sat down with his 11-year-old son, John Wikeira, who was adopted as a baby from Vietnam.

 
JOHN CURTIS: So what are some of your dreams?

 
JOHN WIKEIRA: Well, I kind of want to go to Mars and be an astronaut.

 
CURTIS: What do you think it's going to be like on Mars?

 
WIKEIRA: Red. Yeah.

 
CURTIS: If you don't go to Mars, what else do you think you might want to do?

 
WIKEIRA: Maybe a video game-tester.

 
CURTIS: A video game-tester.

 
WIKEIRA: Even though a video game-tester might be very exclusive.

 
CURTIS: It might be tough. I don't know how many of those job positions there are.

 
WIKEIRA: So do you remember what was going through your head when you first saw me?

 
I thought you were so - can I say beautiful, or do I have to say handsome?

 
It doesn't matter.

 
CURTIS: Well, you were both. I had always wanted to be a parent. So it was a dream I had that I never dreamed would come true, because Papa and I are gay. But we had some friends who started thinking about adoption, and that got us thinking. So we started into the process, and one day, a FedEx truck came down the driveway.

 
And they had a little picture of you, and I knew that I was going to get to be your dad. And it was wonderful. And the first time I ever got to hold you, when I got to feed you your first bottle, I guess in a way, I was concerned that you might be scared or nervous with these new people. But holding you up against my chest, it was just like you fit, like we fit.

 
WIKEIRA: How has being a parent changed you?

 
CURTIS: Oh, it changes everything. Do you think about having a family of your own?

 
WIKEIRA: Yeah, sometimes. And, like, when I have kids, you will get to meet them.

 
CURTIS: That's my dream, too. I love you very much.

 
WIKEIRA: I love you, too.

 
CURTIS: We were always meant to be together.

 
(SOUNDBITE OF MUSIC)

 
GREENE: That's John Curtis with his son, John Wikeira. John Curtis and his partner were married in 2011, and they have adopted a second child. This interview will be archived at the library of Congress, and you can get the StoryCorps podcast at npr.org.

 
Support The Programs You Love
</transcript>
</document>
