<document>
  <title>Songs from a Year of 'Music Lust'</title>
  <date>December 31, 2005 </date>
  <urllink>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5076321</urllink>
  <audlink>http://pd.npr.org/anon.npr-mp3/npr/wesat/2005/12/20051231_wesat_09.mp3?dl=1</audlink>
  <transcript>
     LINDA WERTHEIMER, host: 

 
     If you're looking for the perfect song or any occasion, then Nic Harcourt      is your man.  He's the author of "Music Lust:  Recommended Listening for      Every Mood, Moment and Reason."  Mr. Harcourt is also host of KCRW's      "Morning Becomes Eclectic."  He joins us to talk about his book as well      as some of the best music we may have missed this past year. 

 
     Thanks for being with us. 

 
     Mr. NIC HARCOURT (Author, "Music Lust"):  Thank you so much for asking.      Pleasure to talk to you. 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  The book you've written is basically a big list, a list of      what you consider some of the best music ever, right? 

 
     Mr. HARCOURT:  Well, it's a book of some lists.  You know, when the      publishers actually came to me--and I was in the very fortunate position      of somebody asking me if I would like to write a book, so I figured I      probably should; they might not ask again--I basically started to put      together lists and categories of music that I found interesting, and that      I hoped that other people might find interesting, as well.  And it runs      the gamut, really, from talking about the Rat Pack and the important      records that those guys made to perhaps albums you might have missed.      For example, there's an album that I loved that came out probably around      about 15 years ago by a group called the Liberty Horses.  Never put out      another record, just this one album. 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  How do you--how'd you pick them? 

 
     Mr. HARCOURT:  Basically albums that I felt that perhaps a lot of people      were not aware of.  I mean, Patti Smith is somebody that you know, that I      know, and perhaps people know the name, but how many people really know      Patti Smith's music, especially if you're perhaps 25 years old?  You      know, "Horses" came out 30 years ago now.  If you're a younger person      just getting into music, you might not know Patti Smith's music or the      importance of Patti Smith, so that's why that album is in there. 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  So let's talk about overlooked music from this year.  What's      on your list? 

 
     Mr. HARCOURT:  Well, there's a couple of things.  You know, one of the      brightest moments for me, watching television this past year, was at the      Academy Awards, when Jorge Drexler, who's an artist from Uruguay, won the      Oscar for the best song, original song in a movie.  His song was included      in the movie soundtrack for "The Motorcycle Diaries."  And any of your      listeners who were watching that will remember that he actually wasn't      allowed to perform his song.  They actually had Carlos Santana and      Antonio Banderas perform this song.  When he won the award, he got up on      stage and instead of giving an acceptance speech and thanking everybody      he could think of, he just sang his song a cappella.  That was so      touching to me.  We had Jorge on our program just a couple of weeks after      that and he performed a song for us which we ended up putting on a      compilation CD that we've released of Latin alternative artists called      "Sounds Eclectico," and we're going to play you a track from it right      now.  It's Jorge Drexler. 

 
     (Soundbite of song) 

 
     Mr. JORGE DREXLER (Recording Artist):  (Singing in Spanish) 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  Very tender, that music.  Let's keep going down the list. 

 
     Mr. HARCOURT:  Well, up next is a band called The Magic Numbers.  This is      from a CD that I fell in love with at the beginning of this year when I      got a copy of it as an import from the UK.  My favorite album of the      year--it's self-titled--and we're going to listen to a song called      "Love's A Game." 

 
     (Soundbite of "Love's A Game") 

 
     THE MAGIC NUMBERS (Band):  (Singing) Maybe I've walking in line.  And      maybe you should try to make this time.  I'm an honest mistake that you      made.  Could you make time?  Oh, did you mean, oh, did you mean love is      just a game, broken all the same?  Hey now, I will get over you.  Love is      just a laugh, happens all the time.  Swear I know this much is true. 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  That is straight out of seventh-grade, that one. 

 
     Mr. HARCOURT:  Well, you're beginning to get where I'm coming from,      Linda. 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  I like the name of the group Joy Zipper that's on your list.      Here's a track which is called "Out of the Sun." 

 
     (Soundbite of "Out of the Sun") 

 
     JOY ZIPPER (Band):  (Singing) Sun.  Then it came to me from another      place.  So I buried it.  So I buried it.  Sun.  It came to me the other      day, so unreal, so mannequin. 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  Nic, this also, this track is very poppy and it kind of      reminds me of The Beatles.  Are you back in another decade?  Is that the      deal? 

 
     Mr. HARCOURT:  Yeah, I'm still in the '60s.  I'm four years old right      now. I'm still back in the '60s.  You know, something about this song      just caught my attention.  I can't really explain it.  Joy Zipper, it's      an independent band that's a couple who write music together from Long      Island, New York. They put out this record called "American Whip."  And      that song I just loved. 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  Let's hear another one of your picks.  This is from your      list. This is from the hip-hop artist called M.I.A. 

 
     (Soundbite of song) 

 
     M.I.A. (Hip-hop Artist):  (Singing) People pollute.  Let the pull out.      Let the people pollute.  Let the pull out.  Let the pollute.  Pull out      the pull out.  Let the pull out.  Let the pull out.  Sometime, at the MIA      time, I get the bones to make a (censored).  I get the business, make you      blind. Sometime, at the MIA time, I get the bones to make you blow.  I      get the biz to make you blind. 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  So, Nic, tell us about this one. 

 
     Mr. HARCOURT:  M.I.A. is nom de plume from an artist out of Sri Lanka who      actually resides in London right now, also spent a little bit of time in      New York.  And what she's done with this debut record called "Arula,"      which came out a little bit earlier on this year, is really mix up a lot      of different things, some hip-hop beats.  There's a little bit of raga      from the South Asian continent, and a lot of slang in there as well.      Lyrically, it very much addresses what's going on in the world now, and      this girl's father, actually, is a rebel leader in Sri Lanka and the      Tamil Tigers.  He's still there, apparently.  So she's got an interesting      take on life. 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  Now a number of your picks are British-born or      British-based. Are you promoting the old country? 

 
     Mr. HARCOURT:  Well, you know, it's hard to escape where you come from.      As I said a little bit earlier, I grew up listening to The Beatles.      That's the music that my parents played.  And as a young teen-ager, the      music I listened to was pop music over in the UK.  And I'm always going      to be drawn to that sensibility.  So invariably on my end-of-year lists      there's always a number of British artists. 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  OK, we have time for one more song.  And let's make it the      best, or at least one of the best of the year. 

 
     Mr. HARCOURT:  Well, this last song is actually a song from a Los      Angeles-based group called She Wants Revenge.  And I'm currently working      on a television program called "Love Monkey" as a music supervisor, and      this is a group that we actually put into the program performing live in      the show.  And this song is called "Monologue." 

 
     (Soundbite of "Monologue") 

 
     SHE WANTS REVENGE (Band):  (Singing) We will take love and swear upon the      things that we just can't keep.  And this is the time of night when the      moonlight shines down and we can reveal who we truly are within the      darkest, most depraved of joys. 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  Nic, I think you're doing it again.  This one is kind of      David Bowie? 

 
     Mr. HARCOURT:  Well, they just sound English.  You know, interestingly      enough, they get compared with Interpol, who are actually a band from New      York... 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  Right. 

 
     Mr. HARCOURT:  ...who also sound English... 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  Uh-huh. 

 
     Mr. HARCOURT:  ...and all of--all of these bands... 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  And dress English. 

 
     Mr. HARCOURT:  Well, exactly, in black and the skinny ties.  And all of      these bands, I think, have one thing in common, which is they look back      to that early '80s type of music that was coming out of the UK like, I      guess, Bowie to a certain extent and the Cure and other groups, as well,      like Joy Division, in particular, I think. 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  Well, Nic, thanks very much. 

 
     Mr. HARCOURT:  My pleasure.  Thanks for asking.  Happy New Year. 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  Nic Harcourt is the host of "Morning Becomes Eclectic" on      KCRW in Santa Monica and he's the author of a new book, "Music Lust:      Recommended Listening for Every Mood, Moment and Reason."  For a list of      the music you heard today and to find out how to listen to Nic Harcourt's      show on the Internet, come to our Web site, npr.org. 

 
     (Soundbite of "Monotonous") 

 
     SHE WANTS REVENGE:  (Singing) ...darkest, most depraved of joys.  Into      the (unintelligible) and she'd like to try.  Just give me the safe word      and take your hand and slap me in the mouth, my... 

 
     WERTHEIMER:  This is WEEKEND EDITION.  Scott Simon is back next week.      I'm Linda Wertheimer. 

 
Support The Programs You Love
</transcript>
</document>
