<document>
  <title>What Pa. Victory Means for Clinton</title>
  <date>April 23, 2008 </date>
  <urllink>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=89878016</urllink>
  <audlink>http://pd.npr.org/anon.npr-mp3/npr/day/2008/04/20080423_day_02.mp3?dl=1</audlink>
  <transcript>
MADELEINE BRAND, host:  

 
We're joined now by NPR's David Greene. He's been following the Clinton campaign. And David that Clinton campaign must be overjoyed today. 

 
DAVID GREENE: They are. And they were gloating from the moment they called this race last night, Madeleine, and trying to get their story out before the questions started coming about whether the margin of victory was enough. Because the Clinton campaign I think now is just looking for some sort of number to show that this has changed the race in some way.  

 
And I'll tell you how desperate they were. They put out an email to reporters this morning saying that ABC News was suggesting that they've now pulled ahead of Obama in the popular vote. And if we actually look at that report on ABC News website, here's what is said in full: "by one rightly disputed metric - the popular vote including Florida and Michigan - Clinton has pulled ahead of Obama." But without those "rogue states," as ABC put it, Obama is still up by 500,000 votes.  

 
And so the Obama campaign jumped on them and said that the Clintons are trying to distort the numbers. Now if we saw a rush of superdelegates go to Clinton after this win in Pennsylvania, you know, maybe we could start seeing a measurement, but I think Clinton's really starting to look for some sort of evidence they can present and say this has changed things. 

 
BRAND: So even though the vote still goes on. We go to Indiana next and on and on, North Carolina, et cetera. There's no way that either candidate can achieve the number of delegates needed, so in fact, she and I guess Obama are counting on the superdelegates and they're both counting, or at least she is, counting on Florida and Michigan. 

 
GREENE: That's right. They're counting on the superdelegates and they'll need them and also when it comes to Hillary Clinton just saying you know, why not go on. I mean, nothing has been decided yet, it won't be until the superdelegates weigh in and so she's on to Indiana and then North Carolina tomorrow. And Obama is in Indiana today, both candidates moving on to these other states so we'll be talking a lot more. And hearing a lot more spin in the coming weeks. 

 
BRAND: OK. And we'll be hearing a lot more from you. David Greene covering the Clinton campaign, thank you. 

 
GREENE: Thanks, Madeleine. 

 
Support The Programs You Love
</transcript>
</document>
