<document>
  <title>Woman Calls on World to Look in the Face of AIDS</title>
  <date>December 01, 2006 </date>
  <urllink>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=6557803</urllink>
  <audlink>http://pd.npr.org/anon.npr-mp3/npr/day/2006/12/20061201_day_09.mp3?dl=1</audlink>
  <transcript>
MIKE PESCA, host: 

 
AIDS doesn't discriminate. That was an early slogan in fighting HIV and raising awareness. But think about the Americans who have or had HIV. Which names or faces come to mind? Magic Johnson, Rock Hudson, the rapper Easy-E? 

 
One middle class white woman, who has HIV, realized that there were plenty of people like her and more people needed to be aware of that. Independent producer Lu Olkowski has her story. 

 
LU OLKOWSKI: Regan Hofmann grew up in the tony suburbs of Princeton, N.J. When she went to high school in the 80s, she was terrified of AIDS. 

 
Ms. REGAN HOFMANN: And then, quite frankly, by the mid-90s, I had never heard of a woman - a heterosexual woman who wasn't an IV-drug user -having HIV. I perceived myself to be literally at no risk for HIV. 

 
OLKOWSKI: Unfortunately, in 1996 Regan contracted HIV from her first and only boyfriend after her divorce. Regan was so embarrassed that she kept it a secret. And because she had health care, she could keep it a secret from her friends. For roughly eight years, she told only her immediate family. 

 
Ms. HOFMANN: I would be sitting at a dinner party or just hanging out with my friends and they would make disparaging comments about people who had HIV and it was very hard to keep a poker face. I never said anything or participated in a conversation because I was so fearful. 

 
I think one of the nastiest things I ever heard was from a guy who I actually was considering going out with, and we were at a party and he said, well I think HIV is nature's way of correcting overpopulation and I also think it takes out the people that shouldn't be on the planet. You know, the druggies and the whores and the gays. And I just couldn't believe these things are pouring out of his mouth. Then of course that was the end me wanting to go out with him. 

 
OLKOWSKI: Dating was fraught with problems. Once, after she disclosed her HIV status to a guy she was dating, he changed his phone number and disappeared. As for her friends, they had no idea she was losing weight from the AIDS medication. 

 
Ms. HOFMANN: So I would hear these comments from my friends, you know, oh, you look great, and you're so skinny. And, you know, what every girl likes to hear. And I, of course, was panicked. This fear that the secret would get out was gnawing at me inside, and the stress of that was hard on my body and hard on my mind. 

 
OLKOWSKI: To find an outlet for her anxiety, Regan approached the magazine POZ, short for Positive, a lifestyle magazine for people who have HIV. She ended up writing a regular column under the byline anonymous. And last year, the magazine asked her to come onboard full time. At first, she wasn't really sure if she should. 

 
Ms. HOFMANN: I was worried that I was representative of too small a slice of the pie. But over the years, women have become a larger portion of those. In fact, it's almost 30 percent in the United States are women. And that's a huge jump from a couple of years ago, when women only comprised 7 percent. 

 
OLKOWSKI: Still, Regan didn't want to take the job unless she was going to disclose her HIV status openly. But earlier this year, she became the magazine's editor in chief. 

 
Ms. HOFMANN: Then I put my face on the cover of the magazine and the phone started to ring off the hook, socialites in Texas, mothers of three in Washington, D.C, You know, women living down in SoHo whose husbands are on Wall Street. There are so many women out there like me who are just not coming forward. 

 
OLKOWSKI: So it's probably no surprise that Regan still finds even the most well-meaning people are ignorant about AIDS and HIV. Not too long ago, she was in Washington, D.C., at a charity fundraiser for AIDS research. She was there with another HIV positive woman who works at a magazine, sitting around the big table with other donors. 

 
When Regan mentioned that one in 20 people in Washington, D.C., had HIV, the people at her table didn't believe her. 

 
Ms. HOFMANN: They said that can't be true. And I said yes, it's true. 

 
OLKOWSKI: When they still didn't believe AIDS was a problem in the U.S., she told them that the rate of HIV infection at their table was even worse than in the District of Columbia. 

 
Ms. HOFMANN: And literally their jaws hung open as I told them I was positive and Marvelyn told them that she was positive. And two of the women actually got up and left the table. You know, it might have been coincidence, but I don't think so. These people truly do not perceive AIDS should be in their world. There were people on stage from other countries talking about their experiences and yet there is disbelief on the part of these, you know, upper-middle class American women that there was HIV right in their backyard. I think the thing that people need to in understand is that everybody's face is the face of AIDS. It has always been. 

 
OLKOWSKI: From NPR News, I'm Lu Olkowski in New York. 

 
(Soundbite of music) 

 
PESCA: To learn more about Regan Hofmann and POZ magazine, go to our Web site, npr.org. 

 
Support The Programs You Love
</transcript>
</document>
