<document>
  <title>'Still Looking' Collects John Updike Essays On Art</title>
  <date>November 10, 2005 </date>
  <urllink>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5006080</urllink>
  <audlink>http://pd.npr.org/anon.npr-mp3/npr/me/2005/11/20051110_me_18.mp3?dl=1</audlink>
  <transcript>
     STEVE INSKEEP, host: 

 
     One of the best-known chroniclers of American life also turns his      attention to American art.  John Updike has won just about every major      literary award for his fiction about work, family and home.  He's the      author of novels including "Rabbit Run" and "The Witches of Eastwick."      He's also produced many essays and reviews during his 73 years.  Among      other things, Updike turns his writer's eye to famous American paintings      and a collection of his essays is titled, "Still Looking." Here's NPR      special correspondent Susan Stamberg. 

 
     SUSAN STAMBERG reporting: 

 
     The first thing John Updike saw on waking as a child in Shillington,      Pennsylvania, was a painting of sand dunes his mother bought for $35      during the Depression, so art was important in the Updike home.  From his      earliest years, John Updike went to museums.  He took art courses in high      school. After Harvard, he spent a year at the Ruskin School of Drawing &amp;amp;amp;      Fine Art in Oxford, England.  Even though it turned out that writing was      more important to him than making visual art, he has written about art      for years. 

 
     John Updike is in our New York studio. 

 
     Tell us how you look at a painting.  Your book is full of good color      reproductions.  Let us pick one; the Edward Hopper, "People in the Sun."      That's a very peculiar painting.  I will you'd describe it, John Updike. 

 
     Mr. JOHN UPDIKE (Author, "Still Looking"):  Yeah.  It is put together of      elements that don't really seem to belong together.  There's kind of a      grassy plain in the middle distance.  In the far distance there's a      rather mechanical-looking mountain range.  And in the foreground, on what      seems to be a cement slab, a number of people are sitting in deck chairs,      all facing the sun except for one man who's reading a book.  Well, these      people are getting a kind of southwestern sun bath, let's assume, and yet      they're fully dressed. They're wearing suits.  The woman is wearing what      looks like a very proper dress. 

 
     STAMBERG:  People love Edward Hopper.  You call him a master of suspense. 

 
     Mr. UPDIKE:  Well, because a lot of the paintings do pose a kind of      riddle. What's going to happen next?  What are these people talking      about?  There's a sense of tension.  Often when couples are shown,      there's a sense of the curtain just having been pulled back in a lot of      the paintings, pulled back on a scene that because it's static, we'll      never see develop.  But we can yearn for the development.  We yearn to      know what in time has surrounded this particular moment.  But he always      tells us something about the human mystery, about the sense that being a      human being is a problem, is interesting, is strange, even. 

 
     STAMBERG:  I hope you won't think this is a dumb question, John Updike,      but what do you think the difference is between a painting and a novel? 

 
     Mr. UPDIKE:  The difference, of, well, time.  The painting does not exist      in time.  That's why we like them so much.  We can look at them quickly      or even totally ignore them.  You can go to even an expensive art show in      a couple hours.  A novel takes place in time and it demands time of the      reader.  We seem to be into the novel that fits anywhere, involving,      whereas with a painting we're always a little bit outside of it, aren't      we, looking at it, looking through a window, an invisible window, in      front of it?  And--but it does have the great charm for modern people in      being quickly absorbed, quickly assimilated, at least to a degree.  We      love it.  I love being in museums.  I find that it makes me think about      my writing in a more hopeful way, because there is a certain amount of      dreary circumstantiality about writing, really--you know, the grammar,      the typing, the misspellings, the moving the carriages about, trying not      to bore the reader.  Whereas painting, it just kind of happens.  It      happens right in front of us, and there it is. 

 
     STAMBERG:  And sometimes it tells a story, in a different way, of course.      But let's talk about a painter who doesn't tell stories at all, Jackson      Pollock. You look at him, you see drips, but you look at him, John      Updike, and you see epic drips.  You see something heroic on his      canvases.  What is that? 

 
     Mr. UPDIKE:  The boldness of them and the consistency of carrying through      on the drips, not succumbing to any convenient itch, to pictorialize or      to show images that we can recognize.  It's an ultimate of a kind.  You      can't out-Pollock Pollock.  There have been very few Pollock imitators      because he did it. 

 
     STAMBERG:  Now we go from his drips to such specificity in Andy Warhol,      and he was sort of the next big thing after the action painting of      Pollock.  Soup cans, Coke bottles; somebody said that these were his      still-lifes.  Andy Warhol said, `I like boring things.' 

 
     Mr. UPDIKE:  And I responded to pop painting as homage to everyday      manufactured objects that surround us.  He was not fundamentally painting      Campbell's soup cans in an ironic spirit, saying `Aren't they crass and      cheap?'  No, he was saying they are there.  They are there like flowers      are there or clouds or whatever, and we give them the dignity of making      them into art. 

 
     STAMBERG:  It's often been observed that he was being ironic, that he was      making some kind of a statement and a put-down.  His aim was not to      elevate the soup can. 

 
     Mr. UPDIKE:  If you look at his statements, they sound ironic--`I like      boring things.  I like things to be exactly the same over and over      again.' I'm reading from my own quotations of him.  In another case he      said, `The reason I'm painting this way is that I want to be a machine.'      And then he said, `If you want to know all about Andy Warhol, just look      at the surface.  There's nothing behind it.' That is facing the facts of      modern existence.  There's an awful lot of surface existence with nothing      behind it.  And Warhol in some way caught that and made it, at least in      the paintings, into art. 

 
     I once met Andy Warhol, by the way.  It was at some rich person's party      in Manhattan, and he, I thought, was wearing a tuxedo, and when I tried      to make conversation, remarked upon how strange it was to see him in a      tuxedo.  He unbuttoned his and zipped down his fly enough to show me that      he was wearing beneath the tuxedo, blue jeans.  This could be taken as a      kind of irony.  To me, I took it as a kind of revelation, and an insight      in the man who--behind the tuxedo there with these blue jeans.  He was a      man from a humble background and he was a hard worker.  I kind of feel a      soul mate in Andy Warhol. 

 
     STAMBERG:  It's just that he's from Pennsylvania. 

 
     Mr. UPDIKE:  That's right.  He is from Pennsylvania, the great unironic      state.  In Pennsylvania we don't go in for irony.  We take everything      every seriously. 

 
     STAMBERG:  Thank you very much. 

 
     Mr. UPDIKE:  Thank you. 

 
     STAMBERG:  John Updike.  His newest book is called "Still Looking:      Essays on American Art." I'm Susan Stamberg, NPR News. 

 
     INSKEEP:  And you can read an excerpt from "Still Looking" by going to      npr.org. 

 
     This is MORNING EDITION from NPR News.  I'm Steve Inskeep. 

 
     RENEE MONTAGNE, host: 

 
     I'm Renee Montagne. 

 
Support The Programs You Love
</transcript>
</document>
