<document>
  <title>Cuing Up the Year's Best Music</title>
  <date>November 27, 2005 </date>
  <urllink>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5025103</urllink>
  <audlink>http://pd.npr.org/anon.npr-mp3/npr/wesun/2005/11/20051127_wesun_08.mp3?dl=1</audlink>
  <transcript>
     SHEILAH KAST, host: 

 
     The big music stocking stuffers across America this year will probably      include your Bruce Springsteens, Kanye Wests and Mariah Careys, but our      music director, Ned Wharton, has some CD gift suggestions from off the      beaten path. Here's his annual gift guide for 2005. 

 
     (Soundbite of unidentified song) 

 
     AMADOU AND MARIAM:  (Singing in French) 

 
     NED WHARTON: 

 
     First, music from very far afield, Mali, to be exact.  Amadou and Mariam      met at a school for the blind in the 1970s.  They've been a popular local      act for years and recently burst onto the international stage with help      from musician and producer Manu Chao.  Their new CD, "Dimanche a Bamako,"      celebrates the open-air weddings on a typical Sunday in Mali. 

 
     (Soundbite of unidentified song) 

 
     AMADOU AND MARIAM:  (Singing in French) 

 
     WHARTON:  Also on the world music stage, the Afro Celt Sound System has      been melding global sounds into high-gloss dance music for over a decade.      "Anatomic" is the fifth volume of Simon Emmerson and his group's      exploration of Irish and African musical bonds. 

 
     (Soundbite of instrumental music) 

 
     WHARTON:  Singer-songwriter Imogen Heap has been sequestered in her West      London home studio for years, combing over the intricate sound of her new      CD, "Speak for Yourself." 

 
     (Soundbite of unidentified song) 

 
     Ms. IMOGEN HEAP:  (Singing) Skipping beats, flashing teeth, I am      struggling. 

 
     WHARTON:  Imogen Heap refinanced her mortgage and maxed her credit card      to trick out her new studio and pulled out all the latest gadgets for her      new CD. But there are some low-fi elements, too, including sounds from      electronic toys, passing trains and carpet-packing tubes.  She's recently      come to the attention of American audiences with some music heard on "The      O.C." TV series, including this cut called say "Goodnight and Go," which      is also on the new album. 

 
     (Soundbite of "Goodnight and Go") 

 
     Ms. HEAP:  (Singing) Why'd you have to be so cute?  It's impossible to      ignore you, unless you make me love so much.  It started up, we get along      so well. Say good night and go. 

 
     WHARTON:  So how about some good, old-fashioned rock 'n' roll made in      America? Well, Big Star is back with their first studio album in 30      years.  The cult power-pop band was never quite a household name, but      alternative rock bands from R.E.M.  to The Replacements cite Big Star as      an influence.  The new CD, "In Space," features two new band members, Jon      Auer and Ken Stringfellow from the Posies, along with original players,      drummer Jody Stephens and Alex Chilton, the man who wrote "The Letter" as      a 16-year-old for The Box Tops in 1967.  "Lady Sweet" from the new CD is      an example of Big Star's updated power-pop sound. 

 
     (Soundbite of "Lady Sweet") 

 
     BIG STAR:  (Singing) And I might as well be losing sleep for all the good      it would do me, when the fear of feeling runs so deeply, truly.  Lady      sweet. 

 
     WHARTON:  One of my favorite new indie groups comes from the Silverlake      neighborhood of Los Angeles.  Nominated as best rock band for the LA      Weekly Music Award, Silversun Pickups only whet our appetite for more      with their debut disc.  It's really just an EP, a handful of tunes on a      disc called "Pikul"--that's P-I-K-U-L--a memorial tribute. 

 
     (Soundbite of unidentified song) 

 
     SILVER SUN PICKUPS:  (Singing) ...(Unintelligible) armor, silver rain,      silver rain. 

 
     WHARTON:  If you like what you hear from Silver Sun Pickups, stay tuned.      They're due for a full-length CD sometime next summer. 

 
     A couple of exciting instrumental releases this year should have gotten      more attention.  First this, from the fringes of jazz, the growly groove      of the Hammond B-3 organ in the Benevento Russo Duo. 

 
     (Soundbite of instrumental music) 

 
     WHARTON:  Brooklynites Marco Benevento, who plays keyboards, and drummer      Joe Russo were once a weekly fixture at New York's Knitting Factory.      Their brand of urban jazz seems ready-made for the metropolis with song      titles like the "Vortex" or "Scratchitti," inspired by graffiti scratched      on subway windows. Their new CD is called "Best Reason to Buy the Sun."      And if you're really smitten, you can even go online and download ring      tones of their ditties, such as this one from the CD called "Becky." 

 
     (Soundbite of "Becky") 

 
     WHARTON:  If this frenetic kind of jazz isn't quite the right sound for      your music shopping list, ECM Records always has some titles to cleanse      the palate. Polish trumpeter Tomasz Stanko has been touring and recording      with a talented trio of young players who've been attracting attention as      a band in their own right.  Still under 30, the trio of pianist Marcin      Wasilweski, double-bassman Slavomir Korkevitch and drummer Michael      Miskiewicz once called themselves the Simple Acoustic Trio, but for this      ECM debut they go by their own names for a CD called "Trio." As cold      weather and the holidays arrive, this music is the perfect wintry      backdrop to gently falling snow and hot cider by the fireplace. 

 
     (Soundbite of unidentified instrumental piece) 

 
     WHARTON:  This time of year, as carolers tune up, vocal music rings out.      The San Antonio Vocal Arts Ensemble has always sought out a unique      repertoire, covering Middle Eastern, European and pre-Columbian music.      Their latest release, "La Noche Buena," is a collection of Christmas      music of colonial Latin America. 

 
     (Soundbite of unidentified song) 

 
     SAN ANTONIO VOCAL ARTS ENSEMBLE:  (Singing in Spanish) 

 
     (Soundbite of fiddle) 

 
     WHARTON:  The holidays are a time to remember the neediest.  On December      6th, Nonesuch Records will release "Our New Orleans," a benefit album of      newly recorded songs by New Orleans musicians.  Proceeds from "Our New      Orleans" will help the Gulf Coast rebuild through donations to Habitat      for Humanity. 

 
     (Soundbite of unidentified piece) 

 
     WHARTON:  Artists mobilized quickly for this project, recording over the      course of only a month, but the collection is thoughtful and first-rate,      with performances from everyone from Dr.  John to the Preservation Hall      Jazz Band to Beausoleil.  The CD ends with an iconic tune, Randy Newman's      "1927." 

 
     (Soundbite of "1927") 

 
     Mr. RANDY NEWMAN:  (Singing) It's easy.  It's easy.  It's time to wash us      away.  It's time to wash us away.  It's time to wash us away.  They're      trying to wash us away. 

 
     KAST:  Ned Wharton's director's cuts, including full audio selections,      can be found on our Web site at npr.org. 

 
     This is WEEKEND EDITION from NPR News.  Liane Hansen returns next week.      I'm Sheilah Kast. 

 
Support The Programs You Love
</transcript>
</document>
