<document>
  <title>Marking the D-Day Invasion</title>
  <date>June 06, 2005 </date>
  <urllink>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=4682519</urllink>
  <audlink>http://pd.npr.org/anon.npr-mp3/npr/totn/2005/06/20050606_totn_05.mp3?dl=1</audlink>
  <transcript>
     NEAL CONAN, host: 

 
     This is TALK OF THE NATION.  I'm Neal Conan in Washington. 

 
     Here are some of the headlines of the stories that NPR News is following      today.  The trial of a Florida professor accused of aiding terrorism      started today.  Sami Al-Arian and three other men are charged with      raising money and providing support for the Palestinian group Islamic      Jihad.  And the Supreme Court ruled today that cruise ships registered in      foreign countries but sailing in US waters can be sued if they do not      comply with the Americans with Disabilities Act.  You can hear details on      those stories and, of course, much more later today on "All Things      Considered" from NPR News. 

 
     Tomorrow, lately the Ten Commandments have been the subject of great      controversy over where they should be displayed or where not.  Tomorrow,      war correspondent Chris Hedges joins us for a different take when we talk      about the relevance of the Ten Commandments in modern life--"Losing Moses      Along the Way," tomorrow on TALK OF THE NATION. 

 
     Sixty-one years ago today, 180 US Army Rangers attempted one of the most      difficult and dangerous missions on D-Day--the Allied invasion of      Normandy. They jumped off landing craft amid withering German fire, ran      across a shingle beach and climbed a hundred-foot cliff with orders to      knock out six powerful guns emplaced on top.  Twenty-one years ago,      President Ronald Reagan paid tribute at the monument atop the Pointe Du      Hoc. 

 
     (Soundbite of Ronald Reagan speech from 1984) 

 
     President RONALD REAGAN:  The Rangers looked up and saw the enemy      soldiers at the edge of the cliffs shooting down at them with machine      guns and throwing grenades.  And the American Rangers began to climb.      They shot rope ladders over the face of these cliffs and began to pull      themselves up.  When one Ranger fell, another would take his place.  When      one rope was cut, a Ranger would grab another and begin his climb again.      They climbed, shot back and held their footing.  Soon, one by one, the      Rangers pulled themselves over the top.  And in seizing the firm land at      the top of these cliffs, they began to seize back the continent of      Europe.  Two hundred and twenty-five came here. After two days of      fighting, only 90 could still bear arms.  And behind me is a memorial      that symbolizes the Ranger daggers that were thrust into the top of these      cliffs.  And before me are the men who put them there.  These are the      boys of Pointe Du Hoc. 

 
     (Soundbite of applause) 

 
     Pres. REAGAN:  These are the men who took the cliffs.  These are the      champions who helped free a continent.  And these are the heroes who      helped end a war. 

 
     CONAN:  President Ronald Reagan speaking in Normandy, France, in 1984 on      the 40th anniversary of D-Day. 

 
     In his new book, "The Boys of Pointe Du Hoc:  Ronald Reagan, D-Day, and      the US Army 2nd Ranger Battalion," historian Doug Brinkley describes the      heroic events of that day in 1944 and how that speech by President Reagan      helped change politics and culture in this country. 

 
     If you have questions about what happened on that day 61 years ago or      about the speech 40 years later, give us a call.  Our number is (800)      989-8255, (800) 989-TALK.  And our e-mail address is totn@npr.org. 

 
     Douglas Brinkley joins us from the studios of member station KQED in San      Francisco. 

 
     Nice to have you back on the program. 

 
     Mr. DOUGLAS BRINKLEY (Author, "The Boys of Pointe Du Hoc:  Ronald Reagan,      D-Day, and the US Army 2nd Ranger Battalion"):  Well, thanks for having      me on. I appreciate it. 

 
     CONAN:  Want to talk about both aspects of your book, but let's begin      with the assault itself.  And if you would, tell it through the eyes of      Sgt. Len Lomell, who was one of the Rangers who climbed the Pointe Du Hoc      that morning. 

 
     Mr. BRINKLEY:  Well, first off, the term Rangers--and of course we have      them now, Army Rangers; they're elite fighting men--the term has been      around since the time of the French and Indian War.  In wilderness      communities in Colonial America, you had Rangers who would go and kind of      look for wilderness problems, Native American warring tribes and the      like.  Then the term Ranger continued in our culture in the Civil War.      You had Mosby's Rangers in the Confederacy.  You have Texas Rangers.  But      by the beginning of World War II, Rangers had been a kind of      decommissioned term.  Dwight Eisenhower, George Marshall, FDR wanted to      have a group of elite fighting men, something like the British had with      their commandos.  And eventually the term Rangers was picked. 

 
     And the 1st Ranger Battalion fought in North Africa.  And the second      Ranger Battalion that I wrote about were eventually--they were the best      of the best of the best of the US Army.  They were all volunteers.  They      were trained in Tennessee in the piney dirt-road mountains near      Chattanooga.  They had amphibious training at Ft. Pierce in Florida near      Palm Beach.  They had intelligence training, survivalist training at Ft.      Dix.  And by New Year's Day 1944, they had journeyed on the Queen      Elizabeth to Great Britain and were living in Cornwall.  And these men      did not know what they were being trained for.  They were being trained      for mountain climbing.  Sometimes they would climb straight up, you know,      200-foot walls for training.  They did know that they were going to do      some kind of amphibious landing because those so-called Higgins      boats--but in this case they were British LCAs, landing craft assault      vessels, the ones that you see, like, in "Saving Private Ryan" that could      hold 30 to 37 men in them.  They were training, and suddenly they were      told that spring that they were going to be the first wave at Normandy;      that their mission was mission number one, and that was to take out the      big German guns on the cliffs at Pointe Du Hoc. 

 
     Now Pointe Du Hoc's a hundred-foot-straight-up promontory right in      between Omaha and Utah beaches.  It's a stunning natural sight.  Just      forget the war history there--just standing there and looking over into      the English Channel, it's a beautiful, numbing spot.  But these Rangers      were going to come in on the boats, they were going to fire these special      rockets with grapnels on it that were going to latch on to some hole in      the cliffs.  And they would start pulling themselves up and climbing      while the Germans were shooting at them. 

 
     CONAN:  Almost a suicide mission. 

 
     Mr. BRINKLEY:  It really was.  And of the 225, 99 survived.  And so, you      know, you're losing over half of them.  And yet they knew it.  Colonel      Earl Rudder was their commanding officer.  I spent some time with the      Rudder papers, which are now open at Texas A&amp;amp;amp;M University.  And Rudder      actually went with his men that day--he was wounded--'cause he couldn't      bear to just send his boys out to slaughter and not put himself in harm's      way like they were doing.  And... 

 
     CONAN:  Well, Sergeant Lomell himself was shot just as he was getting off      the assault craft. 

 
     Mr. BRINKLEY:  Well, that's right.  And it's all a buildup.  Len Lomell      is still alive today in Pennsylvania, lives in rural Pennsylvania.  And      he was one of the Rangers who made it to the top.  He was wounded.  He      got there. And they went into these bunkers that the Germans had built      with these giant 155mm guns.  And lo and behold, these big German guns,      the ones that Ike feared were going to blast away our armada, were gone.      They had rollers, and when the Nazis saw in the English Channel that this      was the big D-Day moment, they took the guns and rolled them away about a      mile into a pasture.  Well, nobody knew where the guns were.  These few      Rangers were in firefights with German shoulders on top of the cliffs.      Len Lomell and a man named Jack Kuhn, who I write about--Jack just died      in November--they suddenly just dropped down on their bellies next to a      hedgerow.  And they looked across a meadow about a football field away.      And there were a hundred or so Nazis with one leader with a clipboard      trying to regroup.  They were trying to figure out what do we do now with      the big guns.  And they were going to move them to Omaha Beach and try      to, you know, stop the invasion on that beach. 

 
     So Len Lomell, as all the Rangers were, trained to think quickly.  And he      had three kinds of grenades on him.  One was your typical grenade that      just goes ka-boom.  You know, the second was a grenade that's a flare.      And the third were incendiary or thermite grenades which would create      white heat up to over 3,000 degrees Fahrenheit.  It burns right through      metal, and it makes a hissing noise, but it's generally silent.  So Len      Lomell climbed on his belly with two thermite grenades, put one in two of      the guns and destroyed both guns by melting their firing mechanisms.  He      then... 

 
     CONAN:  And the Germans didn't notice.  And he was able to crawl back,      get more grenades, and destroy the other guns. 

 
     Mr. BRINKLEY:  Well, that's right.  He took out--well, there were      originally six of them.  Allied bombing got rid of one.  So now there      were five.  He just took out two.  And he took the gamble--let's run back      to the coast, let's find some buddies that have thermite grenades, we      need three more.  He got three more, came gain, again crawled on his      belly.  And they were still trying to restrategize, the Nazis.  He put      them in and took out all five of the guns, crawled back.  And while he      was crawling back to safety, he heard a big ka-boom.  There was a ammo      depot that was blown up.  But the point is, the number-one mission, as      Dwight Eisenhower saw it on D-Day, was to take out the guns of Pointe Du      Hoc.  And Len Lomell did that.  And he's one of the great heroes of World      War II. 

 
     CONAN:  And how did this story get missed for the next 40 years? 

 
     Mr. BRINKLEY:  That's a good question.  You know, Cornelius Ryan wrote a      very compelling narrative book, "The Longest Day."  It was made into a      very popular movie.  But the Rangers wouldn't cooperate with him.  One of      the things about Rangers is they don't tell stories on other Rangers.      And there was a feeling that--he did approach Len Lomell and others, and      they just said, `We're not going to tell our stories 'cause it'll seem      like we're bragging.'  So Ryan kind of missed it and wrote up his story      that they got to the top, the guns weren't there, and it was all for      naught.  In truth, a man named Ron Drez, who was a captain in the Vietnam      War and a D-Day expert--he gives tours over there--was the one some years      ago that discovered the real story about the guns and what happened.  And      my book builds on some of his research. 

 
     CONAN:  Let's get some callers on the line--(800) 989-8255 if you'd like      to join us.  Our guest is Douglas Brinkley.  His new book:  "The Boys of      the Pointe Du Hoc and Ronald Reagan, D-Day, and the US Army 2nd Ranger      Battalion." 

 
     Mike is with us on the phone.  Mike's calling from Bishop, California. 

 
     MIKE (Caller):  Hello, thank you. 

 
     CONAN:  Sure. 

 
     Mr. BRINKLEY:  Hi, Mike. 

 
     MIKE:  Yes, I just got a little story I'd like to tell you.  I am a      former 2nd Army Ranger Battalion--a member of the 2nd Ranger Battalion.      And when I served in the '80s, there was a sergeant ahead of me a little      more senior named Matt Ryerson(ph).  And Matt had jumped into Grenada,      and a year later he was selected to go over to Normandy to participate in      that ceremony that you played the tape from with Ronald Reagan giving a      speech. 

 
     And anyway, he said that after the ceremony, all the old Rangers there,      the World War II guys, came over to him and they wanted to hear all about      what the Ranger Battalion is like now, and his mission in Grenada and      everything.  And then Matt of course wanted to hear about their stories.      So they all told him about scaling the cliff and, 40 years later, these      guys still had tears in their eyes as they're telling this story about      how hard it was. 

 
     Well, anyway, the saddest ending to this story is that Matt Ryerson      stayed in the Army and I got out.  And he was involved in the battle of      Mogadishu, which is--you might know that by the "Black Hawk Down"... 

 
     CONAN:  Sure. 

 
     MIKE:  ...book and movie.  And anyway, Matt was killed in action over      there in Somalia. 

 
     CONAN:  I'm sorry for the loss of your friend, Mike. 

 
     MIKE:  Well, he was a good soldier, yes.  That's OK.  But anyway, thank      you for having this show today on this day. 

 
     CONAN:  We appreciate the phone call, Mike. 

 
     MIKE:  OK.  Thank you. 

 
     CONAN:  Bye-bye. 

 
     MIKE:  Bye. 

 
     CONAN:  We're talking with Douglas Brinkley about D-Day and about the      speech that President Ronald Reagan gave at D-Day 40 years later. 

 
     You're listening to TALK OF THE NATION from NPR News. 

 
     And, Douglas Brinkley, Mike did take us to that moment and this      extraordinary speech that Ronald Reagan gave.  You describe in great      detail how speechwriter Peggy Noonan--just her second speech for the      president of the United States--drafted the speech, and all the      infighting that went on, and what was in, what was out.  But the main      idea of this speech, though, was that it was central to something that      you call the new patriotism.  Tell us about that. 

 
     Mr. BRINKLEY:  Yes.  Well, first off, Ronald Reagan became a captain      during World War II, but he stayed Stateside.  He never left American      soil.  That was largely--and I say fully--due to his poor eyesight.  He      could barely see in front of him.  He was near blind.  So he was      disqualified for going abroad in combat.  And the Army Air Corps made      good use of him in both Culver City and then he was in San Francisco,      first, but making training films.  He made over 300 training films during      the Second World War in addition to a couple of theatrical-released films      dealing with World War II.  So he was always in uniform.  People kind of      confused the matinee idol with the war hero.  Reagan kind of seemed to      fulfill both in his persona. 

 
     From that being spokesperson for Army Air Corps, in the '50s Reagan was      spokesperson for General Electric.  And by the 1980s, he was trying to      build what I call the new patriotism, which is embracing of anything      American.  It was a way to bring the Republicans together with more      conservative, moderate Democrats, with Independents based on the flag,      based on America's glorious past.  And the reason this was effective in      the '80s is that our country was quite weary from the Vietnam War.  In      fact, even this past election year, we saw how divisive arguments over      Vietnam can be.  But there wasn't a whole lot to argue about over US Army      2nd Rangers at D-Day or D-Day in general.  It was a moment, one of the      turning points of the 20th century.  The United States were the white      hats, the good guys; we were on the right.  We weren't invading Europe to      conquer it; we were there as liberators.  It succeeded after Normandy and      in the Battle of the Bulge, and eventually the destruction of Adolf      Hitler in Europe. 

 
     So Reagan, who liked morality tales and also liked his American history      very cheery--Gary Wills once said he had a kind of Disneyland version of      American history--it all came to a perfect head for him in June of 1984      because it was a presidential election year, it was the 40th round-year      anniversary of D-Day. And a lot of those D-Day soldiers, you know, and      citizens, and just World War II veterans weren't given a lot of attention      during the tumultuous '60s and '70s. 

 
     In the '80s, with the aid of Time magazine, a Lance Morrow story putting      D-Day on the cover in May of 1984, and then Reagan's going over to      Europe, he was able to use, if you'd like, World War II triumphalism, the      victory of Normandy, the raw courage of these US Army 2nd Rangers, as a      metaphor--the climbing of the hill for freedom--and use it in a Cold War      context.  It was his first great speech.  There are three great Ronald      Reagan presidential addresses.  Peggy Noonan wrote two--`the boys of      Pointe Du Hoc' and then her Challenger disaster speech, and then finally      `Mr. Gorbachev, tear down this wall,' largely written by a man, Peter      Robinson. 

 
     CONAN:  And... 

 
     Mr. BRINKLEY:  But this... 

 
     CONAN:  I just wanted to play the excerpt of the Cold War aspect of that      Peggy Noonan speech at Pointe Du Hoc on the 40th anniversary of D-Day. 

 
     (Soundbite of Ronald Reagan speech from 1984) 

 
     Pres. REAGAN:  In spite of our great efforts and successes, not all that      followed the end of the war was happy or planned.  Some liberated      countries were lost.  The great sadness of this loss echoes down to our      own time in the streets of Warsaw, Prague and East Berlin.  Soviet troops      that came to the center of this continent did not leave when peace came.      They're still there, uninvited, unwanted, unyielding almost 40 years      after the war.  Because of this, allied forces still stand on this      continent.  Today, as 40 years ago, our armies are here for only one      purpose:  to protect and defend democracy. The only territories we hold      are memorials like this one and graveyards where our heroes rest. 

 
     CONAN:  And, Douglas Brinkley, you write, `From 1984 onward, the      Republican Party, following Reagan's lead, became the political party of      the Second World War.' 

 
     Mr. BRINKLEY:  And that's absolutely correct.  What happened was, you      know, Reagan's foreign policy public opinion rating was quite low in      early '84--it was around 37, 38 percent, but it was in the 30s.  By June,      it was up in the 60s and 70s.  The jump was really these speeches.  Mike      Deaver is the great stagecrafter of Ronald Reagan, and he realized how      dramatic Pointe Du Hoc was. And we're only talking about that speech, but      Reagan gave two that day, one at Omaha Beach I also write about.  But the      combo of those two speeches--they were timed to coincide with American      television.  They were on the morning shows.  And it really gave that      morning-again-in-America approach a vitality. And we'll talk about it      after we take a break. 

 
     CONAN:  And without that speech, Douglas Brinkley writes in "The Boys of      the Point Du Hoc," `that there would be no "Band of Brothers," no      "Greatest Generation."  This was the moment when American culture changed      in this respect.' 

 
     Douglas Brinkley joined us from the studios of KQED in San Francisco.  We      thank him for his time today. 

 
     This is TALK OF THE NATION from NPR News.  I'm Neal Conan. 

 
Support The Programs You Love
</transcript>
</document>
