<document>
  <title>Massey Security Chief Indicted In Mine Disaster Probe</title>
  <date>February 28, 2011 </date>
  <urllink>http://www.npr.org/2011/02/28/134143338/massey-safety-chief-indicted-in-mine-disaster-probe</urllink>
  <audlink>http://pd.npr.org/anon.npr-mp3/npr/atc/2011/02/20110228_atc_09.mp3?dl=1</audlink>
  <transcript>
MELISSA BLOCK, host: 

 
This is ALL THINGS CONSIDERED from NPR News. I'm Melissa Block. 

 
MICHELE NORRIS, host: 

 
And I'm Michele Norris. 

 
And we have a quick bit of news now, an indictment related to last year's deadly mine accident in West Virginia. A federal grand jury accuses a security chief at Massey Energy of lying to federal agents and ordering the destruction of thousands of pages of documents. 

 
Here's NPR's Howard Berkes. 

 
HOWARD BERKES: The arrest of 60-year-old Hughie Elbert Stover sends this clear message, according to attorney Mark Moreland. 

 
Mr. MARK MORELAND (Attorney): People need to understand that this is an investigation of the most serious mining disaster in this country in the last 40 years and cooperate fully with all agencies in investigating the tragedy. 

 
BERKES: Moreland represents two of the 29 families who lost sons and fathers in the Upper Big Branch Mine explosion. Stover is the security chief at that and other Massey Energy coal mines. The indictment says Stover trained his security guards to warn mine workers underground when federal mine safety inspectors arrived unannounced, and then he lied about it to the FBI. 

 
Davitt McAteer heads an independent civil investigation of the disaster. 

 
Mr. DAVITT McATEER: Were laws violated? Were regulations disregarded? And were shortcuts taken? I think this indictment suggests that perhaps they were. 

 
BERKES: Stover is also accused of ordering the destruction of thousands of pages of security-related documents. Massey Energy says it notified the Justice Department of the destruction and took steps to recover the documents. Stover is set to be arraigned in two weeks. 

 
Howard Berkes, NPR News. 

 
Support The Programs You Love
</transcript>
</document>
