<document>
  <title>Obama Says Loss in Pa. Won't Hurt His Chances</title>
  <date>April 21, 2008 </date>
  <urllink>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=89823789</urllink>
  <audlink>http://pd.npr.org/anon.npr-mp3/npr/atc/2008/04/20080421_atc_12.mp3?dl=1</audlink>
  <transcript>
MELISSA BLOCK, host: 

 
From NPR News, this is ALL THINGS CONSIDERED. I'm Melissa Block. 

 
First this hour, a conversation with Senator Barack Obama. 

 
Today, he and his rival, Senator Hillary Clinton, campaigned across Pennsylvania today, on the eve of tomorrow's primary there. Pennsylvania is a key contest. Obama is spending heavily and hopes to drive Senator Clinton out of the Democratic race. Nationally, he leads in both the popular vote and in pledged delegates. Clinton is playing up doubts about Obama's readiness to be president. I spoke with Barack Obama earlier today. We reached him on his cell phone. 

 
Senator Obama, welcome back to the program. 

 
Senator BARACK OBAMA (Democrat, Illinois; Presidential Candidate): Thank you so much for having me. 

 
BLOCK: Senator Obama, the most recent Hillary Clinton ad running in Pennsylvania talks about the president needing to be ready for anything, and it shows images of the stock market crash and Pearl Harbor; there's an image of Osama bin Laden, and it quotes Harry Truman. 

 
(Soundbite of political ad) 

 
Unidentified Man: You need be ready for anything, especially now, with two wars, oil prices sky-rocketing and an economy in crisis. Harry Truman said it best, if you can't stand the heat, get out of the kitchen. Who do you think has what it takes? 

 
BLOCK: "Who do you think has what it takes" is the tag line. What is your response to that ad? 

 
Sen. OBAMA: Well, you know, I think the answer is Barack Obama. That may not be the answer she was looking for. 

 
BLOCK: Has what it takes? 

 
Sen. OBAMA: But I - I think that on critical issues of both domestic and foreign policy, Senator Clinton has generally embraced the conventional view. She's oftentimes gone along with the politics of the moment and as a consequence, I don't think she's equipped to actually bring about the changes that are needed to bring different results when it comes to both domestic and foreign policy. 

 
BLOCK: Again, the message there seems to be untested, not ready, dangerous times. 

 
Sen. OBAMA: And, you know, this is a message she's been peddling for the last 15 months. It hasn't been particularly effective, because I think the American people understand they don't need somebody who's going to do the same old things, the same old ways. And they suspect that will result in the same old lack of results. 

 
BLOCK: Your campaign has been reaching out to a key constituency in Pennsylvania. That's gun owners. It's a state with a lot of pro-gun voters. At the same time, if you look at what's happened over the weekend - in your city of Chicago, nine people shot and killed; five gun deaths in Philadelphia, where you are right now, over the weekend. How do you square those two things? 

 
Sen. OBAMA: Well, you know, one of the problems is that we've had gun owners and people who are worried about gun deaths talk past each other instead of talk to each other. And I think if they start talking to each other we can reconcile a tradition of lawful gun ownership in this country with a belief in some commonsense measures to keep guns out of hands of criminals, people who are mentally ill, children. When you talk to the average law-abiding gun owner about the need, for example, to trace weapons that have been used in crimes to where they were sold, so that we can crack down on unscrupulous gun dealers, I think the average law-abiding gun owner agrees with that. The problem is that the debate has gotten so polarized that we don't make much progress. And I think it's important for those of us in urban communities to recognize that people's attitude about guns may be different in different regions of the country, but there's no reason why we can't come together just to make sure that we preserve our traditions but also our children aren't gunned down on the streets. 

 
BLOCK: Do you have a position on the DC handgun ban, the case that's gone before the Supreme Court? 

 
Sen. OBAMA: You know, my general view, and this is colored by having taught constitutional law for ten years, is that as a constitutional matter the Second Amendment probably should recognize an individual right to own firearms. But just because you have an individual right doesn't mean that the public at large doesn't also have a countervailing right to protect the public safety. I mean, we all have rights to own private property, but that doesn't mean that zoning laws are unconstitutional. And I think they will - you know, I don't know all the details and specifics of the DC gun law, but I do know that local communities as well as states and the federal government can institute some commonsense gun laws and that will survive constitutional scrutiny. 

 
BLOCK: Let's talk a little about tomorrow's vote in Pennsylvania. In big states, up until now, New York, Ohio, Texas, you haven't been able to overtake Hillary Clinton and people have said, he has done really well on some solid states but the big states have been a problem. One big state tomorrow, Pennsylvania. 

 
Sen. OBAMA: Well, we're looking forward to, you know, some good results in Pennsylvania, but keep in mind - I just want to question the premise of your question. Illinois is a pretty big state. And you know, maybe it's discounted because it's my home state but my - the last time I checked, New York is Hillary Clinton's home state. California, I don't think that there's any doubt that I would win California in the general election. Virginia which I won handily, Minnesota which I won handily, Georgia which I won handily, all big states. So, you know, there's been a tendency to cherrypick which states are important and which aren't. You know, this is sort of - the bias of our political pundits over the last several years is just to focus on a few states and think that they're the important ones. We think we can win states like Virginia and Colorado that haven't been in play for a very long time and frankly, Senator Clinton couldn't put in play, but I can. 

 
BLOCK: And can you win Pennsylvania tomorrow? 

 
Sen. OBAMA: Well, you know, I wouldn't be campaigning here if I didn't think that we could win, but there's no doubt she had a big advantage here to start with, she comes from a border state that shares a media market with Philadelphia. She had the support of a very popular Democratic governor. But that's why it's hard to extrapolate from what happens during a primary. I don't think there's any doubt that Governor Ed Rendell, the Democratic governor of Pennsylvania, will be pushing hard on my behalf come the general election. The same is true in Ohio with Governor Ted Strickland. So, we feel very confident about our ability to win in November and I feel confident that we'll do just fine tomorrow. 

 
BLOCK: Senator Obama, thank you for your time. 

 
Sen. OBAMA: Thank you so much. Bye-bye. 

 
BLOCK: Barack Obama spoke with me as he was en route from Philadelphia to Pittsburgh. We also requested an interview today with Senator Clinton. 

 
Support The Programs You Love
</transcript>
</document>
