<document>
  <title>Study Details Risk of Drug for HIV-Positive Mothers</title>
  <date>January 10, 2007 </date>
  <urllink>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=6788317</urllink>
  <audlink>http://pd.npr.org/anon.npr-mp3/npr/atc/2007/01/20070110_atc_15.mp3?dl=1</audlink>
  <transcript>
ROBERT SIEGEL, Host: 

 
From NPR News, this is ALL THINGS CONSIDERED. I'm Robert Siegel.

 
MICHELE NORRIS, Host: 

 
And I'm Michele Norris.

 
Researchers say they found a way to work around the problem with a key anti-AIDS drug called nevirapine. It's an inexpensive drug widely used in developing countries to prevent mothers from transmitting HIV to their babies, but sometimes the AIDS virus becomes resistant to the drug.

 
NPR's Brenda Wilson reports.

 
BRENDA WILSON: Giving one dose of nevirapine to the mother during labor and one dose to the child in the day shortly after delivery has spared nearly half of the children in poor countries from acquiring their mother's HIV. But nevirapine is now also widely used in poor countries as part of cheap three-drug combinations for ongoing treatment. In two thirds of the women who got a single dose when they were in labor a resistant virus developed, and later on treatment with the drug failed.

 
In a study published in this week's "New England Journal of Medicine", Dr. Shahin Lockman of Boston's Brigham and Women's Hospital and a group of Botswana researchers found that resistance can be avoided.

 
SHAHIN LOCKMAN: What we found was that women who did not need to start nevirapine-based treatment for their own health because their immune system was still healthy, if they could delay that treatment for six or more months postpartum, their response to treatment was very good and as good as that of a women who had not taken prior nevirapine during labor.

 
WILSON: Lockman says the study and others suggest that the virus that is resisting the drug fades after a period of time.

 
LOCKMAN: In this setting, you're talking about giving one dose of a drug once, and resistance develops; but yes, the virus - in other studies that I've looked at - fades, the resistance virus fades away over time. And the regular virus, which may be more fit or healthy than the resistance virus for a number of reasons, comes back.

 
WILSON: For women who have to start treatment sooner than six months after childbirth there's a different solution. They should be given the full course of anti-AIDS drugs without stopping.

 
LOCKMAN: I think there is consensus everywhere and among many, many people that the women who needed to start treatment shortly postpartum are often women who qualify for treatment during pregnancy.

 
WILSON: That's no simple matter and it represents something of a dilemma. Nevirapine is widely used in developing countries because it's simple to use. But in order to determine who can take nevirapine and who should be on treatment it's going to cost more.

 
Dr. James McIntyre is head of the Perinatal Research Unit at Baragwanath Hospital in Johannesburg, South Africa.

 
JAMES MCINTYRE: Whereas now we can diagnose HIV with a very cheap, rapid pace. If we're going to do further investigations to decide who needs treatment, the one thing that we would like to see is a CB4 count, and that does need additional laboratory capacity, being able to send specimens, get results back and act on those results. But it's not happening in these high prevalence areas where maybe one- third of pregnant women are HIV-positive and the resources are not there yet to put those programs in place.

 
WILSON: But the costs are high in any case. Right now, if treatment with the nevirapine fails due to resistance, the women have to be switched to anti-AIDS drugs that cost more.

 
Brenda Wilson, NPR News, Washington.

 
Support The Programs You Love
</transcript>
</document>
