<document>
  <title>Celebrating a Sister's Memory, on Tape</title>
  <date>January 6, 2006</date>
  <urllink>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5131670</urllink>
  <transcript>
    <paragraph num="0">STEVE INSKEEP, host:</paragraph>
    <paragraph num="1">On Fridays, we bring you moments from the oral history project StoryCorps which gives people a chance to record interviews with friends and family. These recordings are archived at the Library of Congress and excerpts are played here on MORNING EDITION.</paragraph>
    <paragraph num="2">Seven years ago, a young woman named Kendra Webdale was in a New York City subway station when a mentally ill man pushed her in front of an oncoming train. She was killed on January 3rd, 1999. This case is still in the news, still in the courts, and still very much on the minds of family members. Kendra Webdale's sister, Kim Emerson, visited one of the StoryCorps booths to remember the day that her sister died.</paragraph>
    <paragraph num="3">Ms. KIM EMERSON (Sister of Kendra Webdale): I was at home and I got a phone call from--actually a reporter or a journalist from the New York Post and I just let it ring. I was just screening my calls. And she said, `Are you the sister of Kendra Webdale'--and so I heard that and I hopped up to go get the phone--she said, `that was killed on the subway?' And like as soon as I heard the word `killed,' I just--I went to a different place, a place that I've never been before that I felt like I was kind of out of myself.</paragraph>
    <paragraph num="4">I never knew what going into shock was and now when I look back, it was definitely that type of feeling that I just remember falling on the floor and I was just screaming. I was making noises that I didn't even know I was capable of because there's nothing in my life that ever made me scream like that or make a noise like that. And I actually later--I must have been eating an Oreo because there were Oreos like all over the floor. And the worst part about the whole day was knowing that I had to tell my family and I remember standing by my bed and thinking to myself, right now they don't know. Like right now, life is good and I'm going to tell them something so horrible that's going to change their lives and I don't want to do it. And I just remember like waiting, just minutes knowing I had to but just waiting to give them more moments of peace.</paragraph>
    <paragraph num="5">And there was one voice message that Kendra had miraculously left--I had the old answering machines and there was a little tape in it. And there was a full message from Kendra.</paragraph>
    <paragraph num="6">Ms. KENDRA WEBDALE: (From phone message) It's Kendra. It's Monday night at about...</paragraph>
    <paragraph num="7">Ms. EMERSON: I know every inflection in her voice, so she's actually talking on it and talking for like a couple minutes and in the end, she's like, `OK, bye. Love you.'</paragraph>
    <paragraph num="8">Ms. WEBDALE: (From phone message) OK. Bye, love you. Talk to you later. Bye.</paragraph>
    <paragraph num="9">Ms. EMERSON: That is the one thing that I have with her voice on it. And it's one of the most valuable things that I could ever have.</paragraph>
    <paragraph num="10">INSKEEP: That's Kim Emerson remembering her sister Kendra Webdale, who died seven years ago this week when a mentally ill man pushed her in front of a train. Her death led to the creation of a new law in New York state. It's called Kendra's Law and it tries to ensure that people with mental illness take the medications they need.</paragraph>
    <paragraph num="11">To learn more about StoryCorps, you can visit npr.org.</paragraph>
    <paragraph num="12">(Soundbite of sponsorship of StoryCorps)</paragraph>
    <paragraph num="13">INSKEEP: This is NPR News. Transcript provided by NPR, Copyright NPR.</paragraph>
  </transcript>
</document>
